Harold Christy Schwalen papers, 1896-1967 (bulk 1919-1965)
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections
Harold Christy Schwalen papers, 1896-1967 (bulk 1919-1965)
AZ 563
Schwalen, Harold Christy, 1895-1987
Collection includes research notes, maps, blueprints, correspondence, photographs, and other material gathered for his research projects. Includes data from the Department's agricultural experiment stations; surface and groundwater studies; wells and pump irrigation; flow records; climatological data; and manuscript reports and papers. Also includes over 2000 photographs illustrating well drilling, floods and erosion, pumps and pumping plants, irrigation projects, and concrete pipe and ditch construction.
24 linear feet
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections University of Arizona PO Box 210055 Tucson, AZ 85721-0055 Phone: 520-621-6423 Fax: 520-621-9733 URL: http://speccoll.library.arizona.edu/
Restrictions
None.
Biographical Note
Harold Christy Schwalen was born in St. Paul, Minnesota, on August 1, 1895. He moved to Tucson in 1904, where he attended public school. The University of Arizona awarded his B.S., Mechanical Engineering in 1917; M.S., Civil Engineering, in 1925; and C.E. Professional degree in 1946. Between 1930 and 1931, Schwalen attended the Universities of Iowa and Wisconsin for advanced course work in hydrology and geology. Schwalen joined the faculty of the Agricultural Engineering Department in 1919, after two years' service with the 340th Field Artillery in France during World War I. He terminated active service with the University in 1965, having achieved the longest record of full-time service of any person who has ever retired from the University of Arizona.
During his years with the Department of Agriculture Engineering, Schwalen served as Assistant Irrigation Engineer; Assistant Agricultural Engineer at the Arizona Agricultural Experiment Station, Professor and Head of the Agricultural Engineering Department between 1945 and 1959, and Professor and Agricultural Engineer to 1965.The quality of his service was commensurate with the length of time he served the University. His name was virtually synonymous with the University in matters relating to agricultural engineering and particularly with reference to problems of water supply and usage in the state of Arizona.
His research dealt with the location, drilling, and testing of irrigation wells, the design and operation of pumping plants, and the conveyance of irrigation water from the point of supply to crop land. Other work concerned the diversion of flood waters in the recharging of underground reservoirs and the maintenance of water resources. His reports and publications concerning his research have been widely used in furthering water conservation and development in Arizona and the nation.
During World War II, Schwalen was granted leave to accept the appointment, Senior Irrigation Engineer for the Guayule Emergeny Rubber Project U. S. D. A., 1942-1943.
Schwalen held memberships in Kappa Sigma fraternity, the Masonic Lodge, Tucson Rotary Club, and the Old Pueblo Club. He additionally belonged to numerous professional and learned societies. He was a member of the committee on groundwater of the American Society of Civil Engineers; president and director, Arizona Section, American Society of Civil Engineers, president, Pacific Coast Section; and Arizona director of the National Reclamation Association. He is listed in Who's Who in America, Who's Who in Engineering, and American Men of Science.
Organization
This collection is organized into six subgroups.
Subgroup I: Professional and Personal Papers
Subgroup II: Dept. of Soils, Water and Engineering Consulting projects
Subgroup III: Agricultural Experiment Stations
Subgroup IV: Surface and Groundwater Studies
Subgroup V: Water Resource Studies
Subgroup VI: Supplemental papers and photographs
Scope and Content Note
Though some papers date as far back as 1906, the collection mainly contains data from Schwalen's various research projects after 1919. The only personal information deals with his post graduate studies, membership in professional organizations (1939-1963), and records that cover his employment with the University of Arizona (1930-1963).
The remainder of the Schwalen papers contain research notes and calculations, maps, photographs, correspondence, and reports that cover the Dept. of Soils Water and Engineering consulting projects (1931-1966), work at the University's Experiment stations (1922-1965), surface and groundwater studies in Arizona (1917- 1963). Additionally, there is a collection of manuscript reports by Schwalen and others (1914-1952), legal documents and miscellaneous studies on water-related topics. Where dates are absent none could be determined.
Two linear feet of photographs (1919-1966) deal with such topics as floods and erosion, well drilling, pumping equipment, weirs, sprinkler irrigation, adobe construction and others. Original order has been retained due to the difficulty of identifying many of the photos. These are organized by subject or place, and in some cases, by township and range. Approximately 2000 unidentified negatives have been filed under topics or places where possible. The Library would appreciate researchers' help in making further identification.
Recorder strips for Cortaro Farms span the years 1918 to 1964. Individual strips were not retained if summary tabulations were available. This is also true of weather charts. The Library retained charts from 1917-1941, which are years for which we lack published data.
Seperated Material
The collection is liberally illustrated with maps. One box (.4 linear feet) of loose maps have been transferred to the Map Department for separate cataloging.
All duplicate material and most newspaper clippings were discarded. Published pamphlets that bore annotations were kept with the collection, while others (.3 linear feet) were cataloged for general library use.
Access Terms
Schwalen, Harold Christy, 1895-1987 -- Archives
Smith, George E. P., 1873-1975
University of Arizona -- College of Agriculture
University of Arizona -- Agricultural Experiment Station
Cananea Consolidated Copper Co.
Central Arizona Project (U.S.)
Salt River Valley Experiment Station (Ariz.)
Snow surveys -- Arizona
Groundwater -- Arizona
Water supply -- Arizona
Building, Adobe -- Arizona
Agricultural Engineering -- Arizona
Agriculture -- Arizona
Weather -- Arizona -- Observations
Cotton -- Research -- Arizona
Floodplains -- Arizona -- Cochise County -- Management
Floodplains -- Arizona -- Tucson -- Management
Gila River Watershed (N.M. and Ariz.)
Guayule
Salt River Project
Irrigation -- Arizona
Lettuce -- Arizona
San Carlos Indian Irrigation Project (U.S.)
Santa Cruz River (Ariz. and Mexico) -- Floods
Santa Cruz River Watershed (Ariz. and Mexico)
St. David Diversion Dam (Ariz.)
Wellton-Mohawk Irrigation District
Queen Creek Irrigation District (Ariz.)
Rillito Creek Watershed (Ariz.)
Roosevelt Irrigation District (Ariz.)
Golder Dam (Ariz.)
Buttes Dam (Ariz.)
Flowing Wells Irrigation District (Ariz.)
Correspondence
Photographs
Container List
- Subgroup I: Professional and Personal Records
  - Series I: College life, 1930-1931
    Includes Schwalen's lecture notes and reports taken while attending the Universities of Iowa and Wisconsin for advanced studies in sedimentation and structural geology and hydraulic engineering and design.
    - College life, contains lecture notes and printed lecture outlines. 1930-1931 (Box 1)
    - College life, contains lecture notes, reports and papers by Schwalen and others. 1930-1931 (Box 2)
  - Series II: Personal Records, 1920-1965
    Personal material deals only with Schwalen's professional and scholarly career and employment at the University of Arizona.
    - Biographical data. No date (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Employment records, University of Arizona. No date (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Post-graduate studies' correspondence. 1929-1938 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Publications list, H.G. Schwalen. No date (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Series III: Professional Assocations, 1939-1963
    Schwalen was active in a number of professional organizations and the series reflects his interests in working toward development of water resources in Arizona. Contains correspondence, programs, conference papers, and minutes of the various organizations he worked with. He also served on a number of local committees in Tucson; this information can be found in box 23.
    - American Geophysical Union: programs, correspondence. 1940-1951 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - American Society of Agricultural Engineers: annual meeting programs. 1939-1967 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - American Society of Civil Engineers: Arizona Division Minutes. 1952-1954 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - American Society of Civil Engineers: correspondence. 1952-1954 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Arizona-Mexico West Coast Trade Commission: Papers presented. 1961-1963 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Arizona-Mexico West Trade Commission: programs. 1960-1962 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Arizona Power Authority: correspondence. 1945 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Arizona Power Authority: notes and minutes. (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Arizona Power Authority: Organization. 1945 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Arizona Water Resources Committee. 1960-1961 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - National Reclamation Assn. Conferences: Addresses. 1957 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - National Relcamation Assn. Conferences: Addresses. 1957 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - National Reclamation Assn. Conferences: Conferences correspondence and clippings. 1934, 1953 (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - National Waterwell Assn. 1959-1963 (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - Thor Research Center for Better Living Seminar. 1956 (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - Yuma Mesa Soil & Crop Laboratory Annual Conference. 1952 (Box 4, Folder 16)
- Subgroup II: Dept. of Soils, Water and Engineering Consulting projects, 1922-1968
  - Series IV: Correspondence, 1950-1968
    - Correspondence, generated between Dean Phil S. Eckert and Harold Schwalen. 1950-1953 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence, contain a selected sample of general correspondence between Harold Schwalen and various individuals who asked for information on wells, water and irrigation problems. The greater portion of Schwalen's correspondence can be found with the various topics of his research and study. 1950-1968 (Box 5, Folder 2-13)
  - Series V: Guayule Emergency Rubber Project, 1942-1943
    H. C. Schwalen was granted leave from November 1942 through June 1943 to work with the USDA Emergency Rubber Project. The project was designed to study the possibility of developing guayule as an alternative source of rubber. In addition to Schwalen notes and papers, there are numerous reports on water supply and other features of the various irrigation and pumping districts in Arizona as they related to the project.
    - Appointment of Schwalen. No date (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Guayule production, research notes and surveys. No date (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Legislative hearings on Guayule production. No date (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - NR Irrigation survey reports. 1944 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Printed materal, clippings and pamphlets. No date (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Water supply reports of various Arizona districts for Guayule production. No date (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Series VI: Miscellaneous consulting projects, 1922-1966
    The Department carried out a number of special well and irrigation studies throughout Arizona and elsewhere as a service to users.
    - Alabama, Andalusia Groundwater studies, correspondence. 1931 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Alabama, Andalusia Groundwater studies, research notes. 1931 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Arizona (Dragon), Coronado Copper & Zinc, Well logs. 1943 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Arizona (Flagstaff), Arizona Paper & Pulp Co., correspondence. 1960 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Arizona (Flagstaff), Arizona Paper & Pulp Co., maps. (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - Arizona (Flagstaff), Arizona Paper & Pulp Co., well logs. 1954 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - Arizona (Flagstaff), Woody Mountain Well field, report. 1960 (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - Arizona (Phoenix), Arizona Ranches, correspondence and well logs. 1940 (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - Arizona (Phoenix), City of Phoenix, water supply studies. 1940 (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - Arizona (Tucson), State School for the Deaf, correspondence and research notes. 1932 (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - Arizona (Tucson), State School for the Deaf, reports. 1932 (Box 7, Folder 11)
    - Arizona (Tucson), State School for the Deaf, well and pump data. 1922 (Box 7, Folder 12)
    - Arizona (Pima Farms Company), historical data. 1925, 1936 (Box 7, Folder 13)
    - Arizona (Pima Farms Company), pumping computations. 1923 (Box 7, Folder 14)
    - Arizona (Pima Farms Company), seepage studies. 1933 (Box 7, Folder 15)
    - Arizona (Pima Farms Company), water samples. 1929 (Box 7, Folder 16)
    - Arizona (Pima Farms Company), water supply studies. 1933-1932 (Box 7, Folder 17)
    - Arizona (Pima Farms Company), water supply summary. 1933-1936 (Box 7, Folder 18)
    - Arizona (Pima Farms Company), well discharge measurements. 1924-1931 (Box 7, Folder 19)
    - Arizona (Pima Farms Company), well logs. 1919-1920 (Box 7, Folder 20)
    - Sonora (Cananea), Minera de Cananea, report. 1966 (Box 7, Folder 21)
    - Sonora (Cananea), Minera de Cananea, water basin map. (Box 7, Folder 22)
    - Sonora (Cananea), Minera de Cananea, water supply graphs. (Box 7, Folder 23)
    - Sonora (Cananea), Minera de Cananea, well and pump data. 1943-1966 (Box 7, Folder 24)
- Subgroup III: Agricultural Experiment Stations
  Since World War II agricultural experiment stations at state land grant universities have become major research centers involved in both basic and applied research. These were established by the Hatch Act in 1887, and in 1890 Arizona received its first funds for agricultural research. Since then, these stations have become an integral part of the College of Agriculture at the University of Arizona.
  - Series VII: Casa Grande Highway Farm, Tucson, 1916-1955
    Established in 1924 on 105 acres, Casa Grande farm is in the Flowing Wells Irrigation District. It is adjacent to the Santa Cruz River and bisected by highway 10. In the collection it is also referred to as the "new university farm." Contains correspondence and material mainly dealing with construction of irrigation systems. Presently known as the West Campus Agricultural Center.
    - Civil works projects for University Farms. 1933 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence. 1926-1929 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence. 1945-1955 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Location and description. (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Machinery shed specs. 1934 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Maps and charts. (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - Pipeline reports and calculations. 1916-1933 (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - Pipeline weir box specs. (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - Well and pump tests. 1924 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Series VIII: Cortaro and Marana Farms, 1922-1959
    Interested in having a research facility in the Marana area, the University purchased 190 acres from Cortaro Farms. This series includes data on water and wells on both Marana and Cortaro areas. The facility is now known as the Marana Agriculture Center (sometimes referred to as the Marana Experiment Farm in the series). Includes Cortaro Recorder, tabulations of daily water levels of wells taken from continuous water level record. Santa Cruz Recorder, 1939-1942 (no location given), is also included.
    - Static water records. 1929-1945 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Tax appraisal. 1933 (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Water use application. 1938 (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - Water cost analysis. 1937 (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - Cortaro/Marana, Maps and charts. (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - Cortaro/Marana, Well and pump data. (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - Marana Farms, correspondence. 1948-1959 (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - Marana Farms, historical data. (Box 9, Folder 8)
    - Marana Farms, soil analysis. (Box 9, Folder 9)
    - Cortaro Recorder, Interference studies and drawdown curves. (Box 9, Folder 10)
    - Cortaro Recorder, Map and descriptive information. (Box 9, Folder 11)
    - Cortaro Recorder, Well 16C-1. 1946-1962 (Box 9, Folder 12)
    - Cortaro Recorder, Well 16C-1. October 1963-September 1964 (Box 9, Folder 13)
    - Cortaro Recorder, Well 16C-1. March 1965-July 1965 (Box 9, Folder 14)
    - Cortaro Recorder, Well 16C-1. July 27, 1965-February 1, 1966 (Box 9, Folder 15)
    - Cortaro Recorder, Well 16C-1, water depth. 1946-1951 (Box 9, Folder 16)
    - Cortaro Recorder, Well 16C-1, water depth. 1950-1957 (Box 9, Folder 17)
    - Cortaro Recorder, Well 16C-2. 1918-1945 (Box 9, Folder 18)
    - Cortaro Recorder, Well 16C-2. 1939-1945 (Box 9, Folder 19)
    - Cortaro Recorder, Well 16C-2, water depth. 1922-1945 (Box 9, Folder 20)
    - Cortaro Recorder, Well 16D-1. January 5, 1923-December 31, 1923 (Box 9, Folder 21)
    - Cortaro Recorder, Well 16D-1. 1924 (Box 9, Folder 22)
    - Cortaro Recorder, Well 16D-1. January 1, 1925-July 21,1925 (Box 9, Folder 23)
    - Cortaro Recorder, Well 16D-2. August 24,1925-December31,1922 (Box 9, Folder 24)
    - Cortaro Recorder, Well 35D-2. January 1,1926-July 14, 1926 (Box 9, Folder 25)
    - Cortaro Recorder, Well 16F-2. March 10,1922-December 31, 1922 (Box 9, Folder 26)
    - Cortaro Recorder, Well 16F-2. 1923 (Box 9, Folder 27)
    - Cortaro Recorder, Well 16F-2. 1924 (Box 9, Folder 28)
    - Cortaro Recorder,Well 16F-2. 1925 (Box 9, Folder 29)
    - Cortaro Recorder, Well 16F-2. January 1,1926-June 19,1926 (Box 9, Folder 30)
    - Cortaro Recorder, well unidentified. February 23,1958-April 24, 1959 (Box 9, Folder 31)
    - Cortaro Recorder, well unidentified. April 27,1959-March 25,1960 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Cortaro Recorder, well unidentified. May 2, 1960-January 1,1961 (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - Cortaro Recorder, well unidentified. January 1,1961-March 11,1961 (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - Cortaro Recorder, well unidentified. April 2, 1961-September 27,1961 (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - Cortaro Recorder, well unidentified. April 10, 1961-September 27,1962 (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - Cortaro Recorder, well unidentified. April 10,1962-October 21,1962 (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - Cortaro Recorder, well unidentified. October 1, 1962-October 11, 1963 (Box 10, Folder 7)
    - Cortaro Recorder, well unidentified. September 26,1964-March 13,1965 (Box 10, Folder 8)
    - Santa Cruz Recorder, unknown well. 1939 (Box 10, Folder 9)
    - Santa Cruz Recorder, unknown well. 1940 (Box 10, Folder 10)
    - Santa Cruz Recorder, unknown well. 1941 (Box 10, Folder 11)
    - Santa Cruz Recorder, unknown well. 1942 (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - Series IX: Cotton Research Center, 1954-1959
    The 265-acre farm was located in Tempe until 1982, when all research and field work was terminated. It was superseded by the Maricopa Agricultural Center in 1983.
    - Correspondence. 1956-1959 (Box 10, Folder 13)
    - Drilling specs and bid forms. 1958 (Box 10, Folder 14)
    - Irrigation ditches, correspondence and specs. 1956 (Box 10, Folder 15)
    - Permit for well drilling. (Box 10, Folder 16)
    - Proposals. 1954 (Box 10, Folder 17)
    - Well and pump data. 1959 (Box 10, Folder 18)
  - Series X: Dairy Farm
    Now called the Campus Agricultural Center, the 185-acre farm is on Campbell Avenue three miles north of the University.
    - Dairy Farm, specs and maps. (Box 10, Folder 19)
  - Series XI: Mesa Experiment Farm, 1938-1958
    The 160-acre farm was purchased in 1914. It was superceded by Maricopa Agricultural Center in 1983.
    - Fence installation proposals. (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - Lab building specs. 1938 (Box 11, Folder 2)
    - Water system specs. 1958 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Series XII: Poultry Farm, 1949-1959
    This 135-acre farm was established in 1922 and was five blocks north of the University.
    - Maps and charts. 1949, 1959 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Series XIII: Fiver Road Farms, 1961
    The 44-acre farm near Tucson was sold in 1980.
    - Pump installation specs. 1961 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Series IVX: Safford Experiment Farm, 1944-1954
    Also known as the Safford Agricultural Center, the 64-acre farm was established near Stafford in 1946.
    - Correspondence and reports. 1947-1954 (Box 11, Folder 6)
    - Irrigation ditches. 1950 (Box 11, Folder 7)
    - Maps and specs. (Box 11, Folder 8)
    - Water samples. 1945 (Box 11, Folder 9)
    - Wells and pump irrigation. 1936-1944 (Box 11, Folder 10)
  - Series XV: Salt River Valley Experiment Station, 1927-1930
    Harold Schwalen carried out experiments between 1925 and 1929 to determine the effect of different irrigation treatments upon the quality and yield of lettuce. Preliminary study was carried out at the Yuma Valley Farm in 1925 and continued on the Libbart Ranch near the Salt River Valley Experiment Farm in Mesa.
    - Lettuce irrigation, computations. 1927 (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - Lettuce irrigation, fall lettuce. 1929 (Box 12, Folder 2)
    - Lettuce irrigation, project outline. 1929 (Box 12, Folder 3)
    - Lettuce irrigation, soil moisture charts. 1927-1930 (Box 12, Folder 4-9)
    - Lettuce irrigation, soil moisture cross-section. 1928-1929 (Box 12, Folder 10)
    - Lettuce irrigation, soil moisture notes. 1928 (Box 12, Folder 11)
    - Grape project, Yield records. 1926 (Box 12, Folder 12)
  - Series XVI: Yuma Mesa Farm, Yuma Valley Farm, 1921-1956
    The Yuma agricultural centers consist of the headquarters Yuma Valley Center, and the Yuma Mesa Center. The Mesa Farm was established in 1919, covers 240 acres, and is primarily concerned with citrus culture and irrigation requirements for a variety of crops. The 274-acre Valley farm was purchased in 1954, where irrigation ditches are open, concrete-lined V-type. The series deals mainly with ditch construction, and other irrigation and drainage concerns.
    - Yuma Mesa Farm, Ditch specs and bids. 1958 (Box 13, Folder 1)
    - Yuma Mesa Farm, H.B. #12 for repair of building. 1936 (Box 13, Folder 2)
    - Yuma Mesa Farm, maps. (Box 13, Folder 3)
    - Yuma Mesa Farm, soil samples. 1937 (Box 13, Folder 4)
    - Yuma Mesa Farm, underground tile drainage. (Box 13, Folder 5)
    - Yuma Mesa Farm, water delivery contract. 1954 (Box 13, Folder 6)
    - Yuma Mesa Farm, weather records. 1896-1930 (Box 13, Folder 7)
    - Yuma Mesa Farm, well and pump irrigation data. 1925-1948 (Box 13, Folder 8)
    - Yuma Valley Farm, building specs. (Box 13, Folder 9)
    - Yuma Valley Farm, clippings. (Box 13, Folder 10)
    - Yuma Valley Farm, corner ties' specs. (Box 13, Folder 11)
    - Yuma Valley Farm, correspondence. 1946-1956 (Box 13, Folder 12)
    - Yuma Valley Farm, ditch specs and bids. 1956 (Box 13, Folder 13)
    - Yuma Valley Farm, fences and structures' specs and bids. 1957 (Box 13, Folder 14)
    - Yuma Valley Farm, maps and charts. (Box 13, Folder 15)
    - Yuma Valley Farm, maps and charts. (Box 13, Folder 16)
    - Yuma Valley Farm, pipeline correspondence. 1945 (Box 13, Folder 17)
    - Yuma Valley Farm, pipeline proposals. 1954 (Box 13, Folder 18)
    - Yuma Valley Farm, proposed plans for specs for farm. 1954-1955 (Box 13, Folder 19)
    - Yuma Valley Farm, soil profiles. 1951 (Box 13, Folder 20)
    - Yuma Valley Farm, tile drainage. 1951 (Box 13, Folder 21)
    - Yuma Valley Farm, weather records. 1921-1942 (Box 13, Folder 22)
    - Yuma Valley Farm, well logs. 1937-1953 (Box 13, Folder 23)
    - Yuma Mesa/Yuma Valley Farm, ditch specs. (Box 13, Folder 24)
- Subgroup IV: Surface and Groundwater Studies